<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faith of the saints as to a future house and happiness in the other world set forth in a sermon preached at the funeral of that worthy servant of Christ, Mr. Walter Marshal / by S. Tomlyns.</title>
            <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07892753</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07892753</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1216:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faith of the saints as to a future house and happiness in the other world set forth in a sermon preached at the funeral of that worthy servant of Christ, Mr. Walter Marshal / by S. Tomlyns.</title>
                  <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Richardson for Thomas Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marshall, Walter, 1628-1680.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The FAITH of the SAINTS, As to a Future HOUSE and HAPPINESS in the other WORLD.</p>
            <p>Set forth in A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL of that Worthy Servant of CHRIST Mr. <hi>WALTER MARSHAL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>S. TOMLYNS.</hi> M.A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Richardſon,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40313:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40313:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable the Lady <hi>Anne Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> and to the truly Religious Mrs. <hi>Mary Fiennes;</hi> the Author wiſheth increaſe of Grace, and the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Glory, through Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam, Miſtreſs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT hath pleaſed the Lord to afflict and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe you both with Bodily Diſtempers, and every Fit of a Diſeaſe, every Paroxiſm of Pain, is a blow that contributes to the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Tree: theſe Van-curriers of Death do undermine the Vigor and ſtrength of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and help forward the Ruin of a frail Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle. As there are Flowers that blow and wither in the Spring, as well as others that flouriſh and fade in the Summer and Autumn; ſo, many of Mankind do fade and die in the Spring of Youth, as well as in the Summer of Riper Years, and in the Autumn of Old Age. God can make our Night, and Deaths Harveſt to come whenever he pleaſeth; our Sun may ſet, when we think it is not yet Noon; Deaths Harveſt may come, when our Spring ſeems not yet to be paſt. Our Breath is in our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, and may ſoon paſs out; the Judge ſtands
<pb facs="tcp:40313:3"/>at the door, and may quickly enter in: It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us therefore always to be ready for the coming of our Lord, that he may not ſurprize us as a Thief in the Night, but may Viſit us as a Bridegroom that we have long looked and waited for. It is, or ſhould be the work of our whole Week-day, to prepare for the Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sabbath. As by your Bodily Diſtempers, the great Landlord warns you out of your Earthly Tabernacle, ſo the Text I inſiſt on teaches you whither Saints muſt Remove, and what a Houſe God hath built to entertain the ſeparated Souls of Believers. I have therefore thought fit to Tender this ſmall Treatiſe to you, as a Teſtimony of my Reſpect and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance towards you; if it may in any degree prove a Light to your Feet, a Lamp to your Paths, a Staff to your Faith, and a Cordial to your Souls, it will be very acceptable to him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Obliged and Humble Servant, <hi>S. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40313:3"/>
            <head>To my Well-beloved Friends, the Inhabitants of <hi>Goſport</hi> in the County of <hi>Southampton;</hi> the Author wiſheth Grace and Peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IT hath ſeemed good to the Sovereign Lord of Heaven and Earth to make a Breach upon you, by ſnatching away from you a faithful and laborious Servant of Chriſt, who fed you with his Doctrine, and edified you by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: He wooed for Chriſt in his Preaching, and allured you to Chriſt by his Walking. Though the Seedſman be dead, yet the Doctrine he preached is Incorruptible Seed, the Word of God that lives and abides for ever. And though his ſervice by vocal preaching among you is paſt, yet your Account for your profiting by, and growth under his Miniſtry is to come. Look therefore diligently to it, that the Word of God dwell richly, and root deeply in your ſouls; that it be the ſword of the Spirit to ſlay your luſts, a ſpiritual Mould to faſhion your hearts aright, and Bread to feed and nouriſh you up to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life. Walk while you have the light, and work the works of him that ſent you into the World while it is day, build up your ſelves on your moſt holy Faith, and walk in love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards each other as Chriſt hath loved you. Your ſouls came into this World on a Trading Voyage, to buy Gold tried in the Fire, white Rayment and Eye-ſalve. Neglect not your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Traffick, the longer the Merchants ſhip ſtayes out, the richer Lading ſhould it bring home. Lade your ſelves with Treaſures that Death ſhall not ſpoil you of: Adorn your ſouls with Ornaments, that it ſhall not ſtrip off. It will be ſad if any of you ſhould go out of the World, and carry no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing away with you but the guilt of Sin, and the fear of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, a bitter remembrance of paſt iniquity, and a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful expectation of Wrath to come. Death is called the way of all the Earth,</hi> 1 Kings 2.2. <hi>and in this way you muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:40313:4"/>tread, and by it depart from all Friends and Enjoyments below. O look up to, and take faſt hold of Chriſt, that is the Ladder that reaches up to Heaven, and ſo is the way to the beſt Country and Inheritance! You cannot decline the way that will carry you off from all Earthly Relations, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Poſſeſſions. O be ſure that you enter into and walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in that way, that will carry you to an inviſible World of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and Glory! Time haſtens, days poſt away, and will you ſtand idle? You are carried a-pace down the River of Time, towards the Ocean of Eternity, and will you not as ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Racers preſs forward towards the Mark, for the price of the High Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus! Let not by bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs divert you from your principal and moſt noble work.</hi> Mary <hi>choſe the one thing neceſſary;</hi> David <hi>deſired one thing;</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith, this one thing I do: Read thoſe three Scriptures,</hi> Luk. 10.42. Pſal. 27.4. Phil. 3.13, 14. <hi>This argues ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and fervency i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deed, when you chooſe, deſire and do one thing as Neceſſary; and are Converſant about other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters but as indifferent things. Be watchful againſt the old man, that ſtoops you towards this Earth; beware of Satan that wreſtles with you, to throw your minds and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earts down to this World. Lay not thoſe ſnowy-creatures in your boſomes, that will not only melt away themſelves, but alſo chill your Hearts to better and more Noble Objects. Be not guilty of ſuch folly, to magnifie what you are but Stewards of, and to deſpiſe what you may be Heirs of. Take hold of the Hope ſet before you, and then when others ſhall be put away as droſs, you ſhall be made up as Jewels and ſhine for ever in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of your Father. This Sermon as it was Preached at your deſire, ſo now it is Printed with ſome enlargement, at the Requeſt of ſome of you: the Lord accompany it with the teaching of his Spirit and the efficacy of his Grace; that it may conduce to your ſpiritual Good; which is the carneſt deſine and Prayer of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 23. 1680.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your affectionate Friend and Servant for Jeſus ſake, <hi>S. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40313:4"/>
            <head>The Faith of the SAINTS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR. 5.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For we know that if our Earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words of the Text, are a reaſon of ſomewhat diſcourſed and aſſerted by the Apoſtle in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter; in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. he ſaith, <hi>we faint not.</hi> And in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. <hi>We look not at the things that are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen.</hi> And why did he not faint under preſent Preſſures and Afflictions? why did he and other Saints look at an unſeen Happineſs and Reward? To ſuch Queſtions as theſe he Anſwers in the words of the Text, <hi>For we know, that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Words we may obſerve theſe ſeveral Parts.</p>
            <p n="1">I. A Name the Apoſtle gives to the Body, it is our Earthly houſe of this Tabernacle. He calls it an Earthly houſe, and it may well be ſtyled ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe it was taken out of the Earth; <hi>Geneſis.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is maintained and upheld by Food that grows out of the Earth: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.14, 15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Houſe of Clay hath its Foundation on the Earth;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40313:5"/>
               <hi>Job.</hi> 4.19. on this Earth men walk and tread.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It may be ſtyled an Earthly houſe, for into duſt it muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle doth not only call the Body an Earthly houſe, but adds the word Tabernacle, to diminiſh and leſſen the ſenſe of the word <hi>Houſe;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, It is too much to call the body abſolutely a houſe, this word is too high and great for ſuch a frail, brittle, mouldering thing: it is a Tabernacle rather than a Houſe, and ſo the Apoſtle calls it, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. <hi>We that are in this Tabernacle, do groan being burdened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. We have an Intimation of the Frailty of this Earthly houſe; that it would ſoon fall to pieces, and crumble into duſt; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle implies that Ruin was haſtening on it, and that its diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did approach; he grants and confeſſes that it muſt and would ſhortly be diſſolved. The walls of our clay Cottage will moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der down, the boards of our Tabernacle muſt be unpinned, this Tenement of the body will decay and fall to the Earth, and the Soul that is the Tenant, muſt remove, diſlodge and take its flight into E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernity.</p>
            <p n="3">III. We have the gracious and comfortable Proviſion that God hath made for his People when this earthly houſe ſhall be diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the heavens.</hi> Here we may obſerve, that though ſeverity be exerciſed towards our Fleſh and Old Man, that this Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle muſt be plucked down and turned into Ruins and Rubbiſh; yet there is grace extended to the New man. Though the Soul is turned out of one houſe, yet it is taken into another; though it may not ſojourn any longer in a Tabernacle here below, yet it ſhall dwell for ever in a Palace above. When death hath done its worſt, the Saints of God ſhall not be Houſe-leſs or Harbour-leſs. Though Juſtice Raze their Earthly houſe, yet Mercy hath Reared and Raiſed up a better Heavenly Habitation for them; out of which they ſhall never diſlodge or remove. Heaven and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs there to be enjoyed, is ſet out here under the Notion of a houſe: We may obſerve an eſegant Climax in the language of the Holy Ghoſt, and phraſe of the Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes Heaven it ſelf and all the bleſſedneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s is ſtyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Houſe;</hi> as <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2. <hi>In my Fathers houſe are many Manſions.</hi> And then the Place and Happineſs of every particular Saint, is but as one Room, Manſion or Chamber; as in the Palace of an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40313:5"/>Earthly King, there are ſeveral Lodgings and Apartments; ſo in the Royal houſe of the Eternal King there are many Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: by reaſon of which it well deſerves the Name that <hi>Iſaac</hi> gave to a <hi>Well</hi> that he digged, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.22. we may ſtile it <hi>Rehoboth,</hi> which ſignifies as much as Room, Breadth and Large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. In this one Palace of the glorious King there is room enough for all his Subjects to dwell with him, though the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them be more than we can Reckon or Imagine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Heaven and the happineſs of Saints there is called a City; <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>he looked for a City that hath foundations.</hi> So alſo it is ſtiled <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14. A City is made up of many Houſes, and when heaven paſſes under this Notion, every Saint is ſaid to have his particular houſe in it; as according to the words of the Text, every Believer may ſay, that when his Tabernacle is diſſolved he hath a houſe prepared for him in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heaven and its glory hath the name of a Country put on it; and a Country imports ſomething more than a City, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.14, 16. they ſought and deſired a heavenly Country.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Holy Ghoſt aſcends it higher, and uſes a word more large and ſignificant than all the other. Heaven and its Felicity is called a World, <hi>Luk</hi> 20.35. they that ſhall be accounted worthy to obtain that World; <hi>i. e.</hi> the Earthly Paradiſe ſeems to be but a part of one Country (for it was planted in <hi>Eden, Gen.</hi> 2.8.) but how large and ſpacious is the heavenly Paradiſe, which is called a World?</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle doth not only call the place and ſtate of Saints departed from this world, a <hi>Houſe;</hi> but he inſiſts upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and ſomewhat delineates the glory of this houſe. Here are ſeveral expreſſions that deſerve our ſerious Conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is the Author of it, and this commends the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of this houſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>He looked for a City whoſe builder and maker was God.</hi> The Apoſtle in this Text makes uſe of two words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. God doth appear in this ſtructure not only as a Maker, but as a Maſter-builder; as a moſt excellent Artiſt, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> imports; the skill of Divine Wiſdom doth ſhine in this Choice and Exquiſite piece of Work, fitted and framed for the Reception and Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Favourites and Children to Eternity. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tells us, <hi>that God hath garniſhed the viſible Heavens, Job</hi> 26.13. Yet theſe are but the Porch and ontſide of Gods Palace,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40313:6"/>and if that be ſo beautiful and glorious, what then is the inſide?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle commends this houſe for the Duration of it, he ſtyles it Eternal; and what a great and weighty Epithet is this? It is a houſe that ſhall never decay, or need reparation. It is an houſe not made by mans hands, and therefore it is ſo Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent and Abiding. That ſtructure which mans hands have Reared up, mans may hands again pluck down. Where the Builders areweak and mortal, the Building cannot be ſtrong and eternal: As the Workmen muſt fall to the Earth, ſo their work will moulder to duſt; but here an Eternal Builder hath made an houſe of incorruptible Matter, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. and ſo left on his work an impreſs of his own Eternity. This is not a houſe that ſhall Cleave, Founder or Sink, but endure for ever. This City that God hath built, is ſaid to have Foundations; and ſuch that ſhall never be ſhaken or fail. It is a perpetual and abiding City, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14. Here is a ſubſtance induring, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. An inheritance, the beauty and glory of which fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. And a Kingdom that cannot be moved, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. The ſtrongeſt Kingdoms, the greateſt Cities, the moſt ſtately Houſes in the world, have been Subverted, Raz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and utterly Demoliſhed; but this is an Eternal Houſe, City and Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This houſe is commended from the Place and Situation of it; it is a houſe Eternal in the Heavens.</p>
            <p>But you may ſay, Doth this houſe differ from heaven it ſelf, becauſe the Apoſtle calls it an Eternal houſe in the Heavens?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, The houſe of every particular Saint is a part of heaven, and of the bleſſedneſs of the inviſible World; and it is much ſuch a form of ſpeech as if I ſhould ſay, My houſe is in the City, yet it is alſo a part of it: and Oh what an honor is it to poſſeſs and inhabit ſuch an houſe in ſuch a Place? Heaven in Scripture is called <hi>the Higheſt and the Holieſt place, Luke</hi> 19.38. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. Oh what an unſpeakable Dignity and Felicity is this! for Vile, Wretched, Abject Creatures to be entertained in the higheſt and holieſt Place! <hi>David</hi> in the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.5. ſpeaks as if it were too great an honour for ſuch a Mean ſervant as he was, to dwell in the Royal City with the King. Oh how much then are we advanced, by being admitted to dwell with an infinite Majeſty in his Royal City!</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40313:6"/>
            <p n="4">4. We may obſerve the certainty that the Apoſtle and other Believers had of their Title to, Intereſt and Propriety in this bleſſed place, and glorious ſtate. <hi>We know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens:</hi> This was not his or their gueſs or conjecture, 'twas not a meer probable opinion, a looſe and uncertain hope; but we know it, we are fully perſwaded and aſſured of it, and that on good grounds, as Saints may know that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and born of God; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19. <hi>We know that we are of God.</hi> So they may know that God will Treat and Portion them as his Children; as here, <hi>We know we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to theſe four Parts of the Words, I ſhall raiſe and deliver to you theſe four Doctrines.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Doctrine, 1. <hi>The bodies of Saints even as other mens, are but an Earthly houſe of a Tabernacle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctrine, 2. <hi>The Earthly houſe of this Tabernacle muſt be diſſolved.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctrine, 3. <hi>When the houſe of this Tabernacle is diſſolved, yet Saints have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctrine, 4. <hi>Saints do or may know, that when their Earthly Tabernacle ſhall be diſlolved, they have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of each of theſe I ſhall ſpeak with as much brevity as I can.</p>
            <p>Doctrine, 1. <hi>That the Natural Body of Saints, is but an earthly houſe of a Tabernacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is an Earthly houſe; <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.26. <hi>God</hi> is ſaid to make the higheſt Part of the Duſt of the World. Rabbi <hi>Kimchi,</hi> by <hi>Gods</hi> making the higheſt Part of the Duſt of the World, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the Creation of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is exceeding probable. It is a very humbling expreſſion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40313:7"/>of Proud Man, to call him but the higher part of the duſt of the World. Mans body was but one remove from duſt; it was but well colour'd, warm'd and animated Duſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Natural body is a Tabernacle, as it comes from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> it is exceeding weak and frail, and but of a ſhort and Temporary uſe to the Soul, and is not yet fitted to be the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting abode and habitation of it. This word <hi>Tabernacle</hi> is Metaphorical, and the Metaphor is borrowed from Travellers and Soldiers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Travellers had their Tents, eſpecially in Countries where there were not ſuch conveniences as Inns; <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.25. Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling <hi>Jacob</hi> pitches his Tents in a Mountain. Saints are in their bodies as Travellers through this Wilderneſs to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan,</hi> they are ſtrangers in this World, and as Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims journeying on towards the inviſible and future World; as <hi>Jacob,</hi> they are paſſing on towards their Fathers houſe. <hi>We have here no abiding City, but we ſeek one to come, Heb.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saints are in their bodies as Soldiers in a Military Tent. <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> fighting againſt the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> incamped in their Tents, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.11. So Saints are in a Warfare, the beloved City is alſo called the Camp of the Saints; <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. They are fighting againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26. <hi>So fight I not as one that beats the Air.</hi> I am not in jeſt as Fencers, but in good earneſt as Soldiers; I am ſubduing iniquity, mortifying Members on Earth, killing of fleſhly Luſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 1. Here is matter of Humiliation to us all, our bodies are but an Earthly houſe, a weak and frail Tabernacle; why ſhould any ſwell with conceits of their Wealth, or be puffed up with Honour or Profperity, or glory in their Birth or Breeding? They dwell in houſes of Clay, they are clothed and clogged with vile bodies, all their glory and grandeur is but as Tapiſtry hangings or cloth of gold put on or caſt over a baſe mouldering Mud-wall. Theſe bodies that many are ſo proud of, muſt ſhortly be breathleſs, colourleſs Carcaſſes, feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Worms, and ſoiling the graſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 2. We may draw from hence matter of Caution and Counſel.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are our bodies Earthly houſes? Oh take heed that your
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40313:7"/>hearts be not Earthly too, and your Spirits Carnalized alſo! 'Tis Comfortable when there is a heavenly Tenant in this Earthly houſe; but how ſad is it when body and ſoul too are counted but Fleſh by God? <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. <hi>My Spirit ſhall not always ſtrive with man, for that he alſo is fleſh.</hi> How debaſing to man is this expreſſion! though the Soul in its own Nature be a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yet it is ſo debaucht and degenerate, it is ſo ſunk, immerſed into and ſwallowed up in the concerns of the body, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of its diſpoſition and inclination, it may well be called Fleſh. Take heed that your Souls be not thus drenched and ſoaked in bodily Pleaſures and ſenſual delights, that you do not invaſſal, and inſlave your Spirits to be Stewards and Caterers to your Fleſh; that Reaſon be not hired out to the ſervice of a ſenſual Appetite. Unregenerate Perſons are called Men of this Earth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17.14.</note> and Men of this World; their minds fix and dwell on this Earth, their Affections cleave and are glued to it. They are as Plants flouriſhing in their Native ſoil, and as Free Denizens and Citizens of this preſent World.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.35.</note> Oh therefore ſeek that you may be recovered from this Degeneracy, and be reſcued from this Bondage by the renewing of the Holy Ghoſt!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.48, 49.</note> As that which is born of the Fleſh is Fleſh, ſo that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit. The heavenly <hi>Adam</hi> begets a heavenly Seed and Poſterity; if your Souls do now become Spiritual and Heavenly, your bodies in due time ſhall be rendred Spiritual and Heavenly alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If your Bodies be an Earthly houſe, a Frail and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary Tabernacle, then do not put your happineſs on the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle ſtate of the body. Will you confine your Comforts to Minutes and Moments, and not extend your hopes to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Take heed that you live not by ſenſe, walk not after your Eyes, indulge not your Fleſh, give not the Reins to Corrupt Affections. You have Members on Earth, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. and theſe are to be mortified, and not gratified. Oh do not, as <hi>Eſau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16.</note> for one morſel of Meat ſell your Birth-right! do not for ſhort and momentary Pleaſures betray your Souls to Eternal Torments and Miſery! Forbear to give ſatisfaction to ſenſual deſires, put reſtraints on your Luſts,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.23, 24.</note> curb your Appetites and Carnal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, abſtain from fleſhly Affections that war againſt your Souls. God baniſhed our firſt Parents out of Paradiſe, into the Earth and World at large; and ſhall we chooſe our Heaven and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40313:8"/>ſeek our Happineſs in the place of our Exile and Confinement? ſhould we not ſeek after a higher ſtate, and better place for the body than this earth? God hath made our dayes here as an hands breadth; would not that man be counted to have a dim ſight, that could ſee no further than a hands-breadth? and ſhall we look no further? Shall all our Thoughts and Deſires be confin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, and all our endeavours be imployed about a life of a Hands-breadth? Will you not look out of a vile Tabernacle into a World of Glory; and be raiſed above a momentary, to an Everlaſting Life. But I ſhall not ſtay on this, but paſs on to the ſecond Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Doctrine, 2. <hi>That the Earthly houſe of this Tabernacle muſt be diſſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Fabrick of man muſt be taken to pieces, the Soul muſt part with its dear and intimate friend the Body, and put off that garment of Fleſh that cleaves ſo cloſe unto it. <hi>Thou changeſt his Countenance</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>and ſendeſt him away.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 14.20.</note> As in the fourth of <hi>Numbers,</hi> we read of the taking down of the Tabernacle, after it had been ſet up in the Wilderneſs; ſo this Earthly Tabernacle muſt be taken down. And <hi>Ainſworth</hi> makes a Parallel between the taking down of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and the diſſolving of this Earthly Tabernacle. In the pulling down of the Tabernacle, firſt the Holy things were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. and then the Curtains, <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.25. and then the Boards were looſed and unpinned, <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.31. So in the diſſolving of this Earthly Tabernacle, firſt the Soul, that is the moſt Holy thing, diſlodges and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves, and then the Curtains of our Skin and Fleſh are eaten and conſumed by Worms; and then the bones, that are as the Boards and Timber-work of our Earthly houſe and Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, are ſeparated from each other. This Tabernacle muſt be diſſolved, Death will ſoon Plant its batteries againſt this weak houſe; the King of Terrors will ſtorm it with Troops of Pains and Diſeaſes, and entring as a Conquerour, will diſpoſſeſs and eject the Soul from its houſe. This is not a by-law that binds ſome few, but an Univerſal Royal Statute, that ſtands in forde againſt the whole World. <hi>It is appointed for all men once to die, Heb.</hi> 9.27. This Road to the grave is called <hi>the way of all the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40313:8"/>Earth,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.2. And the grave itſelf is ſtyled, <hi>The houſe appointed for all living, Job,</hi> 30.23. Here the Travellers muſt lodge; yea, here the Pilgrims muſt for a great while dwell; and therefore it is called <hi>their long home, Eccl.</hi> 12.5. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this Tabernacle eſpecially in the People of God, is very remarkable, if we conſider theſe three things following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That though their bodies are ſuch a curious Piece of Divine Needle-work, and Architecture,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>acupictus, artificiosè confectus.</hi>
               </note> ſo embelliſhed with Veins, Sinews and Arteries, ſo drawn out into beautiful Limbs, ſo adorned with excellent Features and Comelineſs, yet he that hath Raiſed this excellent ſtructure, will Raze it; he that hath Caſt and Faſhioned this Beautiful Veſſel, will daſh it to pieces; he that hath laid out ſo much Art and Skill on this Choice Piece, will unravel and undo, yea, ſpoil and mar his own Workmanſhip. We may ſay as <hi>Job, Chap.</hi> 10.8. <hi>Gods hands have made and faſhioned us round about.</hi> It is an alluſion to an excellent piece of work, that the hand of the Artiſt hath often gone round, poliſhing and perfecting of it to the higheſt degree: <hi>yet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou doſt deſtroy me.</hi> Oh how wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is this, that God ſhould be ſo diſpleaſed with, and ſeverely turn againſt his own work!</p>
            <p n="2">2. The bodies of the Saints have been the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Know you not that your bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> Yet though they have entertained and harboured ſo glorious a Gueſt, though the Divine Majeſty hath reſided and dwelt in them by a ſpecial Preſence, yet this will not ward off the blow, or guard them from the fatal ſtroke of Death. God dwells, Chriſt lives in this Tabernacle by his Spirit, yet it muſt be diſſolved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Members and Bodies of Saints have been put to a Holy Uſe, and have been imployed as Veſſels of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary; yet this will not ſecure them from death. Though their Life hath been ſpent in ſervice, though their Bodies have been worn out in Labour, and waſted in ſufferings for <hi>God,</hi> yet they muſt be diſſolved. That Tongue muſt be ſtruck dumb that hath praiſed <hi>God;</hi> thoſe Eyes muſt be cloſed. that have been ſpectators of the glory of <hi>God</hi> in the Frame of Heaven and Earth, and have read the wiſdom, power, and goodneſs of <hi>God,</hi> in the Pages of this great Book. Thoſe Members that have ſerved <hi>God,</hi> and miniſtred to his Saints, muſt yet be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40313:9"/>bound with the fatal bonds of Death, and be given up to rot and putrify in the duſt: this ſeems hard and harſh in the eye of Sence and Carnal Reaſon, that the Sacred Lamps of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary ſhould be put out, and thoſe that have been moſt devoted to <hi>God</hi> ſhould be delivered over to Worms and Corruption; and the ſheep of Chriſt be pen'd in Deaths Fold.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But what is the Cauſe of this Severity? why is the Creator ſo diſpleaſed with his Creatures? why doth his Anger ſmoak againſt the very ſheep of his Paſture?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
               </label> I Anſwer. All Men have ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> and therefore die in him; <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. in him we contracted guilt; in him we became liable to Penalties and Puniſhment. We deſcend from a Traytor and Rebel againſt <hi>God,</hi> and have derived from him a Corrupt and Rebellious Nature. It is but Righteous that they ſhould be broken to pieces, that broke off themſelves from <hi>God.</hi> Mans Soul by its Fall was divided from <hi>God</hi> its Life, and thereby deſerved to be turned out of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as its Habitation. Sin is the Worm that kills the gourd of this Natural Life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>The body is dead by reaſon of ſin,</hi> the Plague of Spiritual Leprofie infects this houſe, and provokes <hi>God</hi> to pull it down. The heavenly Husbandman is diſpleaſed with that Soil, that will ſtill nouriſh and feed Satans Tares. The Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, is reſolved and bent againſt the old Frame of Nature, he will pull it down and deſtroy it, and that in his own and beſt People. <hi>God</hi> hath ingaged in, and is, purſuing of a moſt gracious and excellent deſign; and hath drawn an exact draught and idea of the New Creation, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.14.</note> Jeſus Chriſt, to which all the Saints muſt be conformed. This Natural Frame was deſtroyed and utterly aboliſhed in his own Son by Death; and <hi>God</hi> will not uphold that in the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers which he hath taken down and aboliſhed in the Head. The Spiritual and Glorious Body of Chriſt is the great Pattern and Example, according to which all the Bodies of the Saints muſt be Framed and Faſhioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 1. <hi>Information.</hi> From hence we may learn, <hi>Gods</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of, and Severity againſt Sin; <hi>God</hi> threatned the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> that if he did offend and tranſgreſs he ſhould ſurely die, and he will not repeal his Sentence or reverſe his Decree. The Righteous Judge is fixed in his determinations, and inexorable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40313:9"/>as to the Doom he hath paſſed on the Natural bodies of ſinners. As <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.29, 30, 31. God ſware againſt the old Men that came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that they ſhould die in the Wilderneſs; but the New and Young generation, they ſhould enter into and poſſeſs <hi>Canaan:</hi> So <hi>God</hi> hath reſolved that the Old Man ſhall Periſh,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50.</note> that Fleſh and Blood ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of <hi>God;</hi> it is the New Man that ſhall enter into the heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and be heir of the Eternal inheritance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 2. If this Houſe and Tabernacle muſt be diſſolved, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon upon it and expect it. The Maſter will ſhortly take away your Stewardſhip, your great Landlord will warn you out of this Earthly houſe. The Lord of Hoſts will call you to March out of this into another World; live in expectation of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal word, <hi>Return you ſons of Men to your earth and duſt.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.12, 13.</note> Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> ſays, that <hi>he had as a weaver cut off his Life,</hi> and that <hi>he reckoned that God would ſhortly make an end of him.</hi> Conſider you are upon the brink of the Pit, and on the borders of Eternity. Is it not paſt high-water with ſome of you, doth not your ſtrength and vigour Ebb? do not your Lamps burn dim? doth not Death make its near Approaches to you, and begin to ſeize on the Poſts and Out-works of your Senſes? is it not entred already at your Eyes and Ears? as Poſts did run to tell the King of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> that his City was taken at one end; ſo,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.31.</note> may I not ſay that this City of the Body is already taken at one End? hath not Death already invaded and poſſeſſed the Cinque Ports of your Senſes? and ſhall your thoughts ſettle, and your affections Centre on that place from whence you are removing? will you not provide a better habitation, being warned out of this houſe of Clay? will you not ſeek out a New World to plant and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in? are there not numerous Colonies of healed and ſanctified Souls already ſeated in it, and will you not deſire a Lot and Place among them? you have no abiding City here, and will you be wholly deſtitute by neglecting to ſeek one to come? are you ſetting in the Horizon of Time, and will you not make ſure that you ſhall Riſe and Shine for ever in the Horizon of Eternity? Send out Faith as a Spy, into the Heavenly <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an:</hi> Labour to enter into Reſt: Lay hold of the Hope ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you. Improve Time, before the ſpiritual Market is done; before the Ladder that joins Earth and Heaven be drawn up, and the door of the Bride-Chamber be ſhut for Ever.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40313:10"/>
            <p>Doctrine, 3. <hi>When Saints depart out of their Earthly Houſe, they have a Building of God, a Houſe not made with hands, Eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things I ſhall here inſiſt upon:</p>
            <p>Firſt, What this houſe is?</p>
            <p>Secondly, What grounds there are to conclude, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting Saints have and ſhall enjoy this Houſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is to be underſtood by this houſe? I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The glorious Place,
<note n="*" place="margin">Of this place I did ſpeak before, but I ſhall now ſpeak ſomething of the ſtate as it is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the word Houſe.</note> and bleſſed State of the Souls of Saints ſeparated from their Bodies.</p>
            <p n="2">II. This houſe comprehends the Recovery and Happineſs of their Bodies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By this houſe we are to underſtand the glorious Place and State of the Soul; it ſhall mount up to the higheſt Heavens, and dwell there with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>We ſhall be for ever with the Lord.</hi> The glory of <hi>God</hi> is as a Covert and Houſe over the Spirits of Juſt men; <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. it is ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>he ſhall dwell with them;</hi> but <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> He ſhall dwell or tabernacle over them. Oh what a happy change is this, to go out of a vile Tabernacle of fleſh into a Place where the excellent glory of an infinite Majeſty will be as a Tabernacle or Tent over us! The immediate Preſence of <hi>God</hi> will be as a Tent and Houſe to guard us and keep off all Evils, and as a living Fountain to derive all good to us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.15, 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This houſe takes in the Body, and its happy State. Saints do groan earneſtly and deſire to be clothed upon with their houſe from heaven, and by a houſe from heaven the Apoſtle means the Recovery and Reſurrection of the Body, when the Lord from heaven (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47.) ſhall beget it from the dead. When by the arm of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> ſtretched out from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſhall be plucked out of the Jaws of Death. The Soul ſhall not live ſtill as a naked, ejected Spirit, as diſ-ſeized of its habitation; but it ſhall be houſed in the body, and ſeated in its former and ancient dwelling. Though Soul and Body be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorced, yet they ſhall be joined together again; theſe two Friends though long parted, ſhall have a joyful meeting. The grave is a Womb that muſt Travail and bring forth the bodies of the Saints; their ſeed-time ſhall be followed with a harveſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40313:10"/>Death ſhall vomit up its Morſels, this Whale ſhall ſpue out <hi>God's Jonah's,</hi> and then it ſhall itſelf be ſwallowed up for ever. The body that lies in the loweſt grave, ſhall ſit in the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; that which dwells for a time in darkneſs, ſhall dwell in glorious Light for Eternity; that which fed Worms, ſhall feaſt with Angels on the delicious Fruits of the heavenly Paradiſe: and though this was to be accompliſhed at the diſtance of ſome hundreds, if not thouſands of Years, yet the Eagle-Eye of Faith ſeeth it as preſent. <hi>Paul</hi> in his own, and the Perſon of other Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, could boaſt and glory in the Promiſe, as if he were in Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; as if the body were fallen and ſprung up again; as if it were Razed, and Raiſed; as if it were already taken out of the dark Priſon of the grave, and ſeated in the glorious Palace above. <hi>We have</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi> The body, when it ſhall be raiſed and built up out of its Ruines by the Power of Chriſt from heaven, is then fitted to be an Eternal houſe for the Soul in heaven. When Souls ſhall be poſſeſſed of this houſe they ſhall not be found naked, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2, 3.</p>
            <p>Second <hi>Queſt.</hi> What Grounds and Reaſons there are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that departing Saints ſhall have ſuch a houſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This houſe was prepared in the Purpoſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God from all Eternity; he then deſigned a habitation, a place of Reſt and Happineſs for his Elect. The Idea of this great houſe was drawn, the Modul and Scheme of this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous building was laid out in the Mind of the infinite Architect from Everlaſting. As he choſe a peculiar People before the Foundation of the World, ſo he purpoſed to build a place to entertain them in, and to expreſs his love towards them for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Chriſt ſayes, the Kingdom was prepared from, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Foundation of the World; <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. as ſome underſtand that phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God built this houſe and City in the beginning of Time. He ſet his hand to the work, and executed his own Purpoſe and Decree: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>This is a City whoſe builder and maker is God.</hi> Mans hands did contribute nothing to it, it is wholly the product of Divine Goodneſs and Power; and this City <hi>God</hi> is ſaid to prepare for his People.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> needed not ſuch a houſe or City, for he inhabited Eternity; yea, his own Eternity was a ſufficient habitation for him: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40313:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord Jeſus by his Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion and Interceſſion, hath made an entrance into the holieſt place, and prepared a place in Heaven for his People: <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. with <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2. <hi>I go to prepare a place for you.</hi> Though the Kingdom was prepared in the purpoſe of the Father before the World, yet this pleaſure of the Lord was to proſper and to be accompliſhed in and by the hand of the Son as Mediator: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. <hi>The Pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</hi> It was his ſacrifice that did Rent the Vail that was before the Earthly, and did procure an entrance for Saints into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Sanctuary. This Vail ſtood up, and could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by all the ſacrifices of the Law; but when the Vail of Chriſts fleſh was Rent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19, 20.</note> then the way was laid open to the true Holy of Holies; and through the Rent and Torn vail of Chriſts fleſh, we have a paſſage into the heavenly Sanctuary. As the <hi>Red Sea</hi> was divided, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> might have a paſſage through it to the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo by the diviſion and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſts Soul and Body, Believers have a paſſage unto the heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> It is neceſſary alſo that Chriſt do carry in his Blood, and ſprinkle the Mercy-ſeat, and the heavenly Sanctuary with it; that without contradiction from Juſtice, it may become a habitation for thoſe, that once as ſinners, were Enemies to, and Rebels againſt God. And Chriſts blood doth now ſpeak, yea, cry in heaven, for the fulfilling of his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the heirs of Promiſe may partake of the heavenly inheritance: <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. <hi>John.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father, I will that thoſe that thou haſt given me be with me, that they may ſee my glory.</hi> And the Cry of Chriſts Blood cannot be gain-ſayed or denied. Yea, Chriſt as a Fore runner, hath entred into and taken poſſeſſion of heaven for Believers: in which reſpect, while their Perſons are here upon Earth, they are ſaid to ſit in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Places in Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.5, 6. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> had poſſeſſion of the earthly <hi>Canaan</hi> but by the dead bodies of the Patriarchs, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> but Believers have Poſſeſſion of Heaven in a living Fore-runner: and well may the Anchor of their hope enter thither, whither the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner is for them entred: <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19, 20. Chriſt as our high Prieſt is entred within the Vail with the Names of ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> on his breaſt and heart; and he that hath already taken their Names, will in due time take their Perſons, Souls and Bodies too within the Vail.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40313:11"/>
            <p>Laſtly, Chriſtians may be ſaid to have ſuch a building and eternal houſe in heaven, becauſe they are now begotten to the lively hope of it; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath begotten us to a lively hope through the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, to an inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, that fades not away, reſerved in heaven for us.</hi> The hope of this inheritance is not ſo eaſie and common a thing as moſt imagine; this lively hope cannot ſpring up, or be found in a Natural Man; thoſe only that are begotten of God, have ground to hope for his inheritance; thoſe only that are Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and Adopted, have a Right to it, and a Fitneſs for it: And Chriſtians are firſt begotten to a hope, or to a Reverſion; and then they come to Poſſeſſion: as a Child is firſt begotten to a hope of his Father's Eſtate, and afterwards enters upon the enjoyment of it. This hope that is raiſed by Regeneration, and is built on the Death and Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, cannot be fruſtrated or diſappointed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 1. This may Inform us of the wonderful Mercy of God mixed with his Severity. That the Soul is caſt out of its Earthly houſe, this is Severity; that it is received into a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly houſe, this is Mercy. Death is the Executioner of Juſtice, yet it is Chriſt's Harveſt-man alſo: It Cuts off the lives of Men as Offenders, yet it Reaps Saints as good Corn, it gathers them as Sheaves into the Barn, as Wheat into the Garner. A Leaſe of Ejectment is ſealed and ſerved on the Soul by Death, as Gods Officer; the Spirit doth forfeit the houſe of the Body, as a Traytor; yet it is taken into Heaven as an Heir. Oh how wonderful is this, that a man ſhould forfeit and inherit at the ſame time! that the Body ſhould be caſt down to the loweſt grave, and the Soul be raiſed up to the higheſt Heaven! that the one part of Man ſhould dwell with ſuch vile Kindred as Worms and Corruption, and the other part of him ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with ſuch Noble Relations, as God, Chriſt, Angels and Saints are! Oh that God ſhould Tear a man in Pieces, and yet preſently glorifie one piece of him with himſelf! that God ſhould pull off the garment of the Body, and yet preſently cloth the Soul with Celeſtial Glory! <hi>Judas</hi> is ſaid to go to his own place, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25. and God might have adjudged and ſent us to hell, as our own place. We are at beſt but as VVorms and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40313:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40313:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40313:13"/>Graſs-hoppers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 25. <hi>laſt. Iſa.</hi> 40.20.</note> compared with <hi>God;</hi> and did a King ever build a Palace to entertain Worms and Graſs-hoppers in? By ſin we were become as Rebels and Traytors; and do Emperors uſe to build Royal Houſes to Treat and Entertain thoſe that have ſtruck off their Authority, and ſought their lives? O wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mercy! that God ſhould build and furniſh a Palace for us, that might have been ſhut up in the eternal Priſon and Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 2. Exhortation. From this Truth I would draw ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Exhortations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hath <hi>God</hi> prepared ſuch a houſe? Oh labour and ſtrive to be prepared for it:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12.</note> ſeek to the Father to make you meet to partake of this inheritance. Hath <hi>God</hi> built ſuch a glorious houſe, and will he take Swine and Lepers into it? hath he laid out ſuch curious workmanſhip on the Place, and muſt not the Perſons be Refined, Perfumed, Beautified and Adorned that ſhall inhabit it? As the Place is the work of <hi>God,</hi> ſo, muſt not thoſe that ſhall enjoy it, be in a peculiar manner his Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7, 8. The Spouſe of Chriſt is ſaid to have made her ſelf Ready, and to come to the King in Raiment of Needle-work, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.14, 15. That <hi>Iſrael</hi> that is <hi>Gods</hi> glory,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46. <hi>laſt</hi>
               </note> ſhall only enter into this houſe that is the habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Holineſs and of his Glory: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhould make the People of God willing to die, and long to remove from hence: Do we profeſs that ſo many years we have been ſeeking a City and Country Above, and ſhall we be unwilling to find and enjoy what we have been ſo long ſeeking? Shall we not long to poſſeſs the inheritance that is reſerved for us? ſhould our Manſions above ſtill ſtand empty? ſhould that houſe <hi>God</hi> hath built, remain Un-Tenanted? Why like worms are we ſo in love with our holes? why do we go to the Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold and door of our Fathers houſe, with Sorrow and Tears, with Moans and Complaints, as if we were rather entring into the Priſon, than ſtepping into the Palace of <hi>God?</hi> Oh! why do we dote ſo on an Earthly houſe? why are we ſo Fond of a Frail Tabernacle? why is our love ſo inordinate to a vile Cottage? and our deſires ſo weak and languiſhing after our Fathers houſe? is the Footſtool better than the Throne? are our Hutts and Sheds to be preferred before the Manſion Houſe of the Lord of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40313:13"/>
            <p n="3">3. Moderate your ſorrow for the death of godly Friends and Relations. Our loſs is their gain, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. <hi>To me to live is Chriſt, and to die is gain;</hi> they gain a better Houſe, better Company, a better Country; as they were Heirs in Reverſion by the death of Chriſt, ſo they are Heirs in Poſſeſſion by their own death.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.37.</note> As <hi>Barzillai</hi> willingly parted with <hi>Chimham</hi> his Son, ſending him to live with King <hi>David,</hi> in his Royal City and Palace at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> ſo we ſhould freely diſmiſs our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Friends, when they are to croſs the <hi>Jordan</hi> of death, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the True <hi>Canaan,</hi> and live with the King of glory in heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> If a man ſhould ſtrip our Children or Friends of Rags, and cloth them with Royal Robes; pull down their Cottages, and give them ſtrong and ſtately Houſes in the place of them, would we complain? Our godly Friends do make a better Exchange, may not we then command our Souls to return to their Reſt, becauſe the Lord hath dealt ſo bountifully with our Friends, which he hath taken to himſelf? Their Souls enjoy a preſent Harveſt, though it be yet but ſeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with their Bodies; and theſe very Bodies that now are ſowed in the duſt, ſhall ſpring up again to life and immortality. As the Tabernacle was taken down in the Wilderneſs, but ſet up again in <hi>Canaan;</hi> ſo this Tabernacle of our Bodies that is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down by death, ſhall be ſet up again, and being turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrong houſe ſhall ſtand for ever in the heavenly <hi>Canaan. God</hi> favours the duſt of his ſpiritual Temples, and will build them out of their Ruins, that his Spirit as well as our Souls may inhabit them for ever.</p>
            <p>Doctrine, 4. <hi>Saints do or may know, that when their earthly Houſe and Tabernacle is diſſolved, they have a building of God, an Eternal Houſe in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how can they know this? have they a door opened to them into Heaven? can they ſee their Names written over the Manſions taken up for them? have they a window into the Breaſt of <hi>God?</hi> can they read the book of Life? ſearch and peruſe the Myſterious Rolls of Eternity? Is not this a vain Boaſting, or fooliſh Bragging of things that cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood or known.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40313:14"/>
            <p>I Anſwer, True Chriſtians are not miſtaken or deluded, they have ground for what they aſſert, and they may come to know this,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Believing. Faith is one kind of knowledge. It is the knowing of things by the Teſtimony and Record of <hi>God;</hi> and his Word is a ſure Foundation to build Faith on. <hi>God</hi> hath left us a Promiſe of the Everlaſting Reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1. he hath ſet matter of Hope before us in his Teſtimony and Oath, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18. he that believes, takes God at his Word: he that comes in with his Eccho and Amen of Faith to the offers of <hi>God,</hi> ſets to his Seal that <hi>God</hi> is true. <hi>John</hi> 3.33. <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> believed <hi>Gods</hi> Promiſe that he would give them the Earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and it befell them according to their Faith. Other <hi>Iſraelites</hi> diſtruſted <hi>Gods</hi> Power, and rejected his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; and it happened to them according to their Unbelief, they were ſhut out of the Earthly <hi>Canaan: Numb.</hi> 14.8, 9, 28, 29, 30. So thoſe that by the mouth of Faith do kiſs the mouth of <hi>God</hi> ſpeaking in the Promiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to ſalute, and that by Kiſſing; the Patriarks thus ſalut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes by the mouth of Faith.</hi>
               </note> ſhall not be diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; according to their Faith it ſhall be to them. As in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the World of old, he that as the firſt occupant did ſet his foot on a Country, did thereby get a Right to it, even by his taking Poſſeſſion of it; therefore Land was paſſed from one to another among the <hi>Hebrews</hi> by taking off the ſhoe; thereby as it were diſclaiming and renouncing the right that he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſetting his Foot firſt on the Land, <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.3, 7. So truly, whatever we can ſet the foot, and lay the hand of Faith on, we make to be our own; we Claim, Challenge, and et a Right in the Promiſe by believing. This is the Record that <hi>God</hi> hath given us, Eternal Life; and this Life is in his Son: <hi>he that hath the Son hath Life,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. Receiving Chriſt the greateſt gift of <hi>God;</hi> we become intituled to all the other gifts and Promiſes of <hi>God,</hi> that in him are all yea and Amen, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſtians come to know this by inſpection into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſpiritual Experience of a ſaving work wrought on themſelves; <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. <hi>they knew within themſelves that they had in Heaven a more induring Subſtance.</hi> By looking into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they might eſpy ſuch a Divine Nature, ſuch a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Life ſprung up in them, as did evidence they were inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to, and deſigned for the Heavenly Inheritance. As <hi>Mark</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40313:14"/>29.33. the Poor Woman healed by Chriſt, felt it in her Body: and <hi>verſe</hi> 33. She knew what was done in her, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſhe was healed of that Plague. So Chriſts ſpiritual Patients may know within themſelves, what excellent cures this Heavenly Phyſician hath wrought in and on them; and thereby fitted them to Converſe in the True land of the Living. The very ſenſes that an infant hath, do ſhew that it was deſigned for an higher life and larger Place, than ſtill to be impriſoned and penned up in the Womb: its Eyes, Ears, Smelling and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, were to be exerciſed on Objects in this large World: ſo the Spiritual Senſes of the Souls of Saints, do ſpeak them to be deſigned for the inviſible and Eternal World. They can ſee things inviſible, they can taſte ſpiritual dainties, they can ſmell the Odours that come from the Mountain of Myrrh, and the Hill of Frankincenſe; they can ſcent the ſpices of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan. Moſes</hi> his Parents did obſerve his rare and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Beauty, and ſeem from thence to conclude that ſurely he was choſen and deſigned by <hi>God</hi> for ſome extraordinary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.23. And is not the Church of Believers the faireſt among Women? <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.8. and doth not this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and rare beauty evince that Chriſt hath ſet his love on her, and that ſhe is called to the Marriage Feaſt, and deſigned for the Bride-chamber of the Son of God? <hi>Ignatius,</hi> one of the moſt Ancient Fathers, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The living water that did ſpring up in him, did ſay to him within, Come home to thy Father.</hi> Chriſt hath written a living Epiſtle in their Minds and Wills, The Life and Law of <hi>God</hi> as a byaſs on their Hearts, inclines them to another Country and World. They have the firſt Fruits of their Inheritance, the earneſt of the bargain, the beginnings of Everlaſting Life abiding in them already;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.</note> that glorious Company that they ſhall converſe with for ever, are now come down to ſojourn in their hearts here below. The Father and Son dwelled in them by the ſpirit, and ſurely ſuch Royal gueſts will in due time remove the Souls that entertain them, to their own glorious Habitation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is the Myſterious Teſtimony of the Holy Spirit; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16, 17. <hi>The Spirit himſelf beareth witneſs with or to our Spirits, that we are the Sons of God, and if Sons then Heirs,</hi> &amp;c. Surely ſome very high Evidence and Aſſurance is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40313:15"/>by theſe words, whether mediate or immediate I ſhall not now determine. The ſpirit himſelf beareth witneſs; this phraſe imports that the Spirit himſelf excellently appears in this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and will it Teſtifie; and can it not make Souls to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand its voice, to perceive its meaning, to embrace its Teſtimony, and acquieſce in its Evidence? Shall any queſtion or doubt whether men may know themſelves to be the Sons of <hi>God,</hi> when it is one Office and great work of the Holy Spirit to make them underſtand it, and to aſſure their Souls of it? Is the Teſtimony of the Spirit Dark, Intricate, and Ambiguous? doth it leave Souls in hovering ſuſpence, and wavering uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty? when it comes to give its evidence, can it not decide and determine the Controverſie, and make an end of ſtrife in an unbelieving Heart? And if the Spirit doth clear up our Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, may we not know we are Heirs? All Gods Children are Heirs; every Son hath the Rights, Priviledges and Inheritance of a firſt born.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> 1. Oh be Exhorted, Stirred up and Quickned, to ſeek and obtain the ſweet and comfortable knowledge of what is provided for you in Heaven! Strive to aſſure to your ſelves, that you have a houſe built, a City prepared for you above! Oh how uncomfortable is it to be at uncertainties whither we ſhall go, how we ſhall be diſpoſed of, and where we ſhall be fixed for Ever! We know we muſt remove from hence, but how will this damp our ſpirits, when we know not whither we ſhall remove! We know what we muſt part with; but how will it Chill and Deject us, when we know not what we ſhall poſſeſs in another World! Our love cannot be ſo Fervent, our Joy ſo Strong, our Praiſes ſo Hearty and Affectionate, if we know not that <hi>God</hi> is our Father; that he will divide a Rich Portion to us, and ſettle a glorious Inheritance on us. The knowledge of what is reſerved for us in Heaven, will have great influence on our Holy Calling, and will both Quicken us in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſupport us in Suffering the Will of God. Uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all diligence to attain the full aſſurance of Underſtanding of Faith, and of Hope; all which are mentioned in theſe following Scriptures; <hi>Col.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11. Theſe three do make an excellent and comfortable Syllogiſm; the full Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Underſtanding, as to the Terms and Tenders of the Goſpel, maketh the Major; the full Aſſurance of Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40313:15"/>and applying this Doctrine to our ſelves, makes the Minor; and the full aſſurance of Hope, is the ſweet Concluſion, that reſults from theſe excellent Promiſes. O Chriſtians, why, are you contented to live at ſo low a Rate? why are you ſo held in doubts and ſuſpence about your Everlaſting ſtate? why are you ſo loſt in an intricate Wilderneſs, and entangled in ſuch uncomfortable Labyrinths? why is there yet ſo dark a Vail on your minds, that hinders you from looking with Joy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort into another World? Doth not the Goſpel diſpenſation under which you live, afford grounds for high Faith and ſtrong Conſolation? Are we not told, that <hi>God</hi> was in Chriſt reconcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World to himſelf, not imputing their Treſpaſſes to them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. that Chriſt hath made an end of ſin, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Satan, overcome the World, aboliſhed death, and brought Life and Immortality to Light? <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. <hi>laſt.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. Is not Heaven purchaſed and Poſſeſſed for, and bequeathed in Chriſts Teſtament to the Heirs of Promiſe? Are not all that fly for Refuge, to take hold of the hope ſet before them, accepted and allowed to be Heirs of this glorious inheritance? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. Is not this ſentence not exceeding full and comprehenſive? <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son; that whoſoever believes in him ſhould not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life, Joh.</hi> 3.16. and is not this Teſtimony clear and expreſs, that <hi>God</hi> hath given to us Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and this Eternal Life is in his Son; and he that hath the Son hath Life? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. This Life is now poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and enjoyed by Chriſt, and he that receives Chriſt and hath propriety in him, hath alſo Title to it. Will you ſuffer Satan to wrangle you out of ſuch Clear, and wreſt from you ſuch Comfortable and Reviving Texts of Scripture? will you not Echo your Aſſent of Faith, to this good Word of <hi>God,</hi> and take hold of the Hope that is ſet before you? We have more food and abundant ſupports for Faith in this new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſpenſation, and therefore Faith is now ſaid to be come; <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23, 25. and Hope in a more excellent way is ſaid to be ſet before us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. And is it not a diſhonour to this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious new Teſtament diſpenſation for Chriſtians to walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to live in continual Doubts and Fears about their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Condition? The Teſtament of the Son of <hi>God</hi> is Ratified and Eſtabliſhed by his Death; <hi>God</hi> hath promiſed and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40313:16"/>ſworn to bleſs the Heirs of Promiſe; and why ſhould you not apply the Comfort of both to your ſelves; and ſay as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>the Lord hath been mindful of us, and he will bleſs us, Pſal.</hi> 115.12. <hi>God</hi> hath ſpoken in his Holineſs, take him at his Word, and you ſhall find that he will not deny his Promiſe, or go back from it. Let not Satan darken your minds, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief perplex your ſouls with needleſs Objections, it is by Grace that you muſt be ſaved.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33.</note> The Kingdom of Glory is <hi>Gods</hi> free gift to men, and the Righteouſneſs that qualifies for it, is wrought in them by his Spirit. A new Heart is freely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, as well as Eternal Life; both are the gifts of God through Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 36.26, 27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>laſt.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive therefore, and truſt on Jeſus Chriſt for them both. As the Chriſtian Sabbath is the firſt day of the week, and ſo our Reſting-day is before our working-dayes; ſo truly we muſt enter into a ſpiritual Reſt by Faith in Chriſt, our Conſciences muſt be ſprinkled, purged and pacified by his bloody, before we can ſerve the living <hi>God, Heb.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. Chriſt died for ſinners, came into the World to ſave ſinners; and thoſe that ſee themſelves to be ſuch, muſt look to and truſt on Chriſt for Healing and Sanctification, for Grace and Glory, or elſe all Mankind muſt be excluded. Here is no fear of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption or deceiving our ſelves, provided that we deſire and rely on Chriſt for his whole Salvation, for deliverance from the Power as well as the Guilt of Sin. Apply your ſelves therefore to Jeſus Chriſt, receive him, and you ſhall in and with him receive an abundance of Grace and of the gift of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17.</note> and ſo Reign in Life for evermore. If you believe in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 1.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> is your <hi>God</hi> and Father; and if you are Sons, you are Heirs; the Kingdom of glory, the heavenly Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is yours. Match with Chriſt, get into him who is the true <hi>God</hi> and Eternal Life; 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. and he will provide you a place, and make you welcome in his Fathers houſe for ever. <hi>If you have the Son, you have life:</hi> None that belong to him, can be ſhut out of the Banqueting-houſe and glorious Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You that are true Chriſtians be exhorted to rejoyce in your Habitation: ſay to your Souls, that your Lines are fallen to you in pleaſant places, and you have a goodly heritage: have you not a Reſt and Houſe above the reach and rage of Satan
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40313:16"/>and his inſtruments? When they have done their utmoſt they can but conſume you on earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.87. they cannot quench your ſpiritual life, or raſe your heavenly houſe. If you are thruſt out of this World, you have a better Country to enjoy; if you are diſpoſſeſſed of your houſes, you have a more laſting habitation to enter into. When cruel Enemies ſtoned <hi>Stephen,</hi> they could not hinder him from placing his Jewel in a ſafe hand, from committing of his Soul to Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. Why are your Souls Clouded? why do your Spirits droop? why do your hands wax Feeble? Let this Truth Chear and Incourage you, that ſo great an inheritance is bequeathed to you, ſo glorious a houſe is prepared for you in heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Do you know that you have an Eternal Houſe built for you in heaven? Oh then, let this Truth raiſe your Minds and elevate your Hearts to Heaven! Oh let your Converſation be in Heaven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. Chriſt hath ſaid, where the Treaſure is there the heart will be alſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.21. If this eternal houſe be prized as your Treaſure, will it not be a Loadſtone to draw up your hearts to heaven? Why do you weary and wound your ſelves among the Briars and Thorns of this wretched Wilderneſs, when your Minds might Converſe in the delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heavenly Paradiſe? Why do you grovel on the ground, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Dunghil, and feed on Duſt; when you might ſoar up to the Throne, and Feaſt with Chriſt at his Table; ſatisfying your ſelves with the fatneſs of his houſe, and drinking of the Rivers of his Pleaſures? Oh ſet your Affections on, and ſeek the things that are above; <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2. Let your Loins ſtand girt; ſuffer not your Minds to get looſe, fall down, and draggle on this low and dirty World. Chriſt by his Aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath fixed a new Centre, towards which the Minds and Hearts of all Believers ſhould move, and in which they ſhould ſtay and Reſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2, 3.</note> Chriſt hath prayed that all his People may be with him, and he hath prepared a glorious place to entertain them in; and yet ſhall our Minds ſtay, and our hearts dwell here below? ſhall we deſpiſe that now, that we muſt Feaſt on to Eternity? ſhall we be ſtrangers to our everlaſting home? and forget our heavenly Country? Oh Chriſtians why do your Minds ſo often and ſo much leave the Gueſt-Chamber, and the upper Rooms of <hi>Immanuels</hi> houſe? why do you ſo often come down, and delight ſo much to dwell in the low Rooms and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40313:17"/>ground Chambers of this World, can you not meet with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient delights, and full ſatisfaction above? Is the Air on the Mountain of Myrrh, and the Hill of Frankincenſe too pure and fine for your groſs and carnal hearts? O ſeek to Chriſt to cure your ſpiritual diſeaſe, and to recover your Appetite to ſpiritual enjoyments! Oh beg him to take off your weights of Unbelief and Carnal Affections! and give you wings to mount upwards! that as Children you may live on the Fatneſs and Dainties of your Fathers houſe; and as Citizens of Zion, you may delight your Souls on the delicious Fruits of the Tree of Life, and in the pure River of Living water, that Flows from the Throne of God and the Lamb.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40313:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
